nysed.gov 2006-12-14

# Internet Privacy and Security Policy

| 

Resources for:  
  
---  
- Citizens  
- Individuals with Disabilities  
- Licensed Professionals  
- Parents  
- School Administrators  
- Students  
- Teachers  

Information about:  
  
- Grants & Finance  
- Higher Education  
- Laws & Regulations  
- Licensing & Certification  
- Museum, Library & Archives  
- PreK-Adult Education  
- [SED Online Services](http://portal.nysed.gov/) \- A link to NYSED Portal  applications and more.  
   
RSS News Feeds  
|  |  |  [SED Home](http://www.nysed.gov/) > Disclaimers and Notices > **Internet Privacy and Security Policy**   

Internet Privacy and Security Policy

**NEW YORK STATE EDUCATION DEPARTMENT (SED)  
PRIVACY OF YOUR ONLINE INFORMATION AT THE SED WEBSITE**   
 NYSED posted this updated privacy policy on June 17, 2002  in response to the Internet Security and Privacy Act and in recognition of the growing public interest in and concern for information privacy. Your online privacy is important. This section of the State Education Department’s Website provides information about this agency's approach to information from online visitors as well as general information about online privacy. 

This section of the Website is divided into several topics. You can scroll through the entire section. Or you can go directly to one of the topics listed below and on the navigation bar above.   

| **TOPIC 1.**|  SED Internet Privacy Policy  
---|---  
**TOPIC 2.**|  Details on SED Online Information Practices  
**TOPIC 3.**|  General Information about Internet Privacy  
**TOPIC 4.**|  General Information about Cookies and Web Bugs  
**TOPIC 5.**|  General Information about Children's Online Privacy  
**TOPIC 6.**|  Click here for Contact Information  
  
* * *

TOPIC 1. SED INTERNET PRIVACY POLICY

This section describes the State Education Department's online information practice regarding the information collected from visitors to our Website and ways in which the office uses and maintains this information. 

The SED Website has three main purposes:

  1. Provide useful information concerning educational policy and practice in New York and a description of the work of the State Education Department.  

  2. Provide a means to communicate with staff of the State Education Department. You can use this Website as a convenient alternative to mail or telephone communication.  

  3. Provide an electronic medium for local educational agencies to submit data  and conduct business with SED 

The SED Website collects two kinds of information: 

  1. Information you decide to give us, which may include personally identifiable information (PII); and  

  2. Non-personal information your computer automatically provides to every Website you visit. This is sometimes referred to as "navigation" information. The SED retains this information only for a short time.

 Click here for details on information your computer automatically transmits. 

  | **Information you decide to give the SED** | **Information your computer automatically transmits to all Websites**   
Click here for details  
---|---|---  
**How the SED uses information you provide** | The SED Website provides a convenient way to communicate with the State Education Department in addition to the more traditional means such as mail, phone or in-person visits. For example, you can

  * send  SED staff  messages or 
  * request information 

SED retains this information and protects it just as if you had sent it by mail. | SED temporarily retains the information automatically sent by your computer to evaluate the traffic through the SED Website to help make the site more user-friendly.  
**Personally Identifiable Information (PII)** | Personally identifiable information  is information about you, such as your name, address, or social security number, that someone could use to identify or locate you. 

The SED acquires PII online when a visitor sends it. If you browse through the SED Website - reading, printing, or downloading information such as consumer brochures or press releases—you **do not** transmit PII. 

The SED only uses PII for authorized government purposes, for example, authorizing information when processing payment claims or collecting data via web-based applications 

Click here for details on PII.

| Automatic information typically does not personally identify you. Even when it could,  SED does not try to discover or use your identity. 

Click below for details on: 

  1. Identifiability of domain names and IP addresses.
  2. SED use of information your computer automatically transmits.

**Sensitive Information** | There may be particular privacy concerns with certain kinds of information such as financial or medical records. SED uses such information **only** for authorized government purposes. | Automatic information typically does not include any sensitive information about you. 

Click on the following topics for details on: 

  1. Information your computer automatically transmits.
  2. SED use of information your computer automatically transmits.

**Information practices the SED does not use** |  SED does not have a profile database of all online visitors. |  SED does not use persistent cookies, clear GIFs ("Web bugs"), or any kind of anonymous identifier to try to track or recognize you  from visit to visit.

Click here to learn more about cookies.

SED does not draw conclusions about you based on pages you view or search terms you enter.  
  
**Data sharing and transfer** | 

  1. SED does not sell or rent information provided by online visitors. 
  2. SED may share or disclose certain information you provide if necessary to fulfill government functions, such as mediating a complaint. 

Click here for details on sharing information you provide the SED.

| SED does not sell or rent the automatic navigation information your computer transmits.  
**Data security, integrity, and retention** | 

  1.  SED does not store information submitted by all our visitors in an office-wide, master database. 
  2. SED takes appropriate technical measures to protect the security and integrity of information the SED receives. 

  3. Access to information provided by visitors online is limited to SED personnel who have authorization to access the data. 

  4. The same rules of confidentiality that apply to information you might send the SED offline apply to information provided online. 

| 

  1. SED temporarily stores the automatic navigation information in a computer database. After six months, it purges this information from the SED databases. 
  2. SED takes appropriate technical measure to protect the security and integrity of this information. 

**The following notices apply generally to any information the SED receives:**   

**Exceptions** | 

  1. Legal obligations to disclose information: SED may disclose information to comply with a court order, authorized law enforcement request, subpoena, or a request under federal or state "freedom of information" law. 
  2. Emergency exceptions: If necessary to protect health or safety in an emergency situation, the SED may use, share or disclose information other than outlined in this policy. 

  3. If there are other exceptions or special needs for handling information in a specific case, the SED will provide notice as appropriate. 

---|---  
**Notice of changes  
in this Privacy Policy** | If any of the information in this section changes in a material way, SED will post 30 days advance notice on the Home page of this Website, with the effective date of the change. Where a specific page is affected specifically by a change in policy,  SED will post a clear and conspicuous notice.  
**Links to other Websites** | This Privacy Policy applies to the Website of the State Education Department of the State of New York. While the SED offers links to other Websites that may be of interest, SED disclaims any responsibility for their content and cannot vouch for their information practices.  
  
Back to Top

* * *

TOPIC 2. DETAILS ON SED ONLINE INFORMATION PRACTICES

**Details: **

**Personally identifiable  
information you  
give the SED**

| Many visitors to the SED Website provide personally identifiable information for a particular purpose. For example -

  1. If you send the SED a message and want a reply, the SED needs at least your name and your e-mail address or telephone number. 
  2. If you request a publication, the SED needs your name and street address to send it to you. 

  3. If you are the authorized agent for a local educational agency which transacts business over the internet (e.g. submitting required data or processing payment payment claims).  

Back to Top  
---|---  
**Details: **

**Sharing information you  
give the SED**

| The SED may need to share your information to perform government functions, just as if you had sent the SED the information by mail. For example -

  1. If you request that the SED mediate a  complaint against a local school district, SED might require the details of the complaint, which may include your identity.   

  2. If you apply for employment, the SED may need to contact your references and perform other appropriate verification. 

Back to top  
**Details: **

**Information your computer  
automatically provides  
to all Websites**

| While you are browsing, your computer automatically provides certain "navigation" information to every Website you visit, including the SED Website. The navigation information includes:

  1. The address (also known as URL, short for "uniform resource locator") of any Web page you visited before you linked to an SED Web page. 
  2. Your Internet Protocol address (or "IP address"). This is the Internet's address for your particular computer. A Website's computer must know your IP address so the site can send the Web page you ask to view.  
Click here for more details on domain names and IP addresses.

  3. The Web-browsing software you are using. 

  4. Whether your computer is configured to display English or some other language. 

  5. Your online service provider. 

  6. Note: Your computer _does not_ automatically provide your e-mail address. 

For example, if you have an AOL account, were visiting a page on the Yahoo site, and clicked on a link to the SED home page, your computer would transmit to the SED Website that: 
  1. You are an AOL subscriber; 
  2. You use a particular browser software version such as Internet Explorer 5.0. 

  3. You were just visiting a particular page on www.yahoo.com. 

  4. You linked to **www.nysed.gov** on a particular date at a particular time. 

Back to top  
**Details: **

**Use of information  
your computer automatically  
provides to all Websites**

| The SED Website uses automatic navigation information for internal, site-monitoring purposes.

  1. This data allows SED staff to measure visitors' interest in different sections of the Website, so the SED can make the site more useful to visitors. 
  2. The SED generates internal reports that identify the number of web users on a given day who requested pages through particular online service providers. This information may report the volume of requests originating from a service provider associated with a particular school or company or from foreign countries.

**The SED does _not_ :**

  1. analyze our visitors' automatic navigation information to attempt to identify unique or repeat visitors 
  2. routinely retain permanent records of automatic navigation information
  3. attempt to identify individual visitors by analyzing their IP (Internet Protocol) addresses except in cases of attempted security breaches and/or intrusions.

Click here for details on identifiability of domain names and IP addresses.

Back to top  
  
**Details: **

**Identifiability of domain  
names and IP addresses**

| 

  1. **Identifiability of your domain name** : If you access the Internet through facilities provided by an organization such as your school or business, your automatic navigation information may reveal the name of your organization. For example, a student's navigation information might let a Website know that the student accesses the Internet through www.myuniversity.edu. 
  2. **Geographic area** : Similarly, if you access the Internet through an Internet Service Provider (ISP) located in a particular geographic area, a Website may be able to use the ISP's identity to infer that to be your geographic location. 

  3. **Identifiability of your IP address** : Whether your IP address is identifiable depends on whether it is dynamic or static. If it is dynamic, your ISP (Internet Service Provider) assigns a different IP address for each online visit that does not identify any person or machine. 

In contrast, if you access the Internet through an ISP that assigns you a static or fixed IP address (for example, DSL or cable modem service), your IP address will always be the same, and will identify your computer. 

Back to top  
  
* * *

TOPIC 3. GENERAL INFORMATION ABOUT INTERNET PRIVACY

SED handles information about visitors to the SED Website in the following manner:   

**Notice and disclosure** | SED provides notice and disclosure of its information practices by posting its privacy policy.  
---|---  
**Choice/ Consent** | SED receives your online information only when you choose to disclose it, for example, by submitting an online complaint form or request for information. SED only uses this information for the purpose for which you disclosed it, except when the law or emergencies require the SED to do otherwise.  
**Access** | Because the State Education Department is an  agency dealing with information about children, it must carefully safeguard information. Access to personally identifiable information is  limited only to authorized staff.  If you need information you previously gave SED, please contact this office, and, if known, the bureau working on your initial request.  
**Security** | The SED takes reasonable measures to protect the security and integrity of information received. The SED periodically purges its computer files that log activity on the SED Website.  
  
Back to Top

* * *

TOPIC 4. GENERAL INFORMATION ABOUT COOKIES AND CLEAR GIFs ("WEB BUGS")

Although the SED does not use persistent cookies or clear GIFs ("Web bugs") on this Website, many sites do use this technology. Here is some helpful information. 

**Cookies   
 **

**A cookie is...** | 

  * A cookie is a small data file placed on your hard drive by a Website so it can "remember" information about you or your computer. 
    * A Website may assign you an ID and create a temporary cookie with that ID number on your computer. 
    * The Website then can create a profile with your ID number on the Website's server. 

    * In your profile, the Website can store information about your interests and other characteristics. For example, a site that carries news and weather might record your zip code so it can display local weather and news each time you visit the site. A credit card or bank site might use your profile to store your password, so that it has a way to recognize you and display your account information. 

  * A cookie can be read and updated only by the Website that created it. One Website cannot "peek" at another Website's cookies. 

---|---  
**A cookie is not...  ** | 

  * A cookie is not a program. It is a data file. 
  * A cookie is not a spy device that can read files on your computer. 

  * A cookie is not a way for a Website to secretly discover your personal information.  

**Cookies on your computer** | 

  * To learn more about cookies on your computer and what you can do about them, consult your browser's help or tutorial feature. 

**Clear GIFs or "Web bugs"  
 **

**A clear GIF is...** | 

  * Another common way that web sites collect information about you is by using technology called clear GIF or "Web bug" (also referred to as a "1-by-1 GIF," "pixel tag," or "Web beacon"). 
  * A clear GIF is an invisible image that can be imbedded in a Web page or certain kinds of e-mail. ("GIF" stands for "graphical interface format," which is one of the technologies used to show pictures in a Web page.) 
  * As with cookies, a Website can use clear GIFs to collect data about you. 
  * Unlike cookies, clear GIFs are not stored on your computer. 
  * Unlike cookies, most browsers do not have built-in features to explain or help you detect clear GIFs. 

---|---  
  
Back to Top

* * *

TOPIC 5. GENERAL INFORMATION ABOUT CHILDREN'S ONLINE PRIVACY

The SED does not solicit information from children under the age of thirteen. If the SED receives information submitted by children under the age of thirteen, those communications are accorded the same protections as if the information had been submitted offline. 

The Children's Online Privacy Protection Act of 1998 ("COPPA") imposes restrictions on commercial Websites, not government agency websites. Although COPPA does not apply to the SED Website, the SED practices are consistent with its mandates. If you would like more information about COPPA, please visit the FTC's official COPPA page at: 

<http://www.ftc.gov/bcp/conline/pubs/online/kidsprivacy.htm>   
Back to Top

* * *

TOPIC 6. SED CONTACT INFORMATION

If you have questions about the SED Website privacy statement or this Website, please contact the SED by e-mailing the Information Security Officer at [ infosec@mail.nysed.gov](mailto:infosec@mail.nysed.gov)

You can also write SED at: 

> > David Walsh  
>  Chief Information Officer  
>  State Education Department - Room 121 EB  
>  Washington Avenue   
> Albany, New York 12234 

Back to Top  
---  
  
[Board of Regents](http://www.regents.nysed.gov/) | [Disclaimer and Notices](http://usny.nysed.gov/notice.html) | [Employment Opportunities](http://www.oms.nysed.gov/hr/) | [Internet Privacy and Security Policy](http://usny.nysed.gov/privacy.html) | [NYS Archives](http://www.archives.nysed.gov/) | [NYS Library](http://www.nysl.nysed.gov/) | [NYS Museum](http://www.nysm.nysed.gov/) | [Office of Counsel](http://www.counsel.nysed.gov/) | [Office of Cultural Education](http://www.oce.nysed.gov/) | [Office of Elementary, Middle, Secondary and Continuing Education (EMSC)](http://www.emsc.nysed.gov/) | [ Office of Higher Education](http://www.highered.nysed.gov/) |  [ Office of Operations and Management Services](http://www.oms.nysed.gov/) | [Office of the Professions](http://www.op.nysed.gov/) | [Office of State Review](http://www.sro.nysed.gov/) | [Office of Vocational & Educational Services for Individuals with Disabilities (VESID)](http://www.vesid.nysed.gov/) | [Program Office Listing](http://usny.nysed.gov/programs.html) | [Report Fraud, Abuse, and Waste](http://www.oms.nysed.gov/oas/fraud/index.html)  
  
New York State Education Department  
89 Washington Avenue  
Albany, New York 12234

**If you have a question or comment about any of the NYSED program areas or topic areas, please contact:  
[webadmin@mail.nysed.gov](mailto:webadmin@mail.nysed.gov) or call (518) 474-3852 or check the NYSED Functional Telephone Directory at <http://usny.nysed.gov/phone/> .**

If you are a person with a disability and you have a problem accessing the content on this web site,   
please contact: [webadmin@mail.nysed.gov](mailto:webadmin@mail.nysed.gov) or call (518) 473-4501. 

Please Note: The number (518) 473-4501 is **NOT** to be used to request or inquire about professional licenses, student testing, teacher certification, teacher certificates, teacher certificate extensions, the TEACH system, education degrees (i.e. GED diplomas or high school/college transcripts), or any other NYSED program area or topic.

For individuals experiencing problems with the TEACH System, please go to [ https://portals.nysed.gov/tcert/technical.htm](https://portals.nysed.gov/tcert/technical.htm)   
or call (518) 486-6041. 

For individuals unable to access the State Aid Management System (SAMS), please call the SAMS help desk at   
(518) 474-2978 or email [ omssams@mail.nysed.gov](mailto:omssams@mail.nysed.gov). 

For any questions regarding teacher certification, teacher certificates or teacher certificate extensions, please call (518) 474-3901   
or go to <http://www.highered.nysed.gov/tcert/contact.htm>

For any questions regarding GED exams, GED diplomas, or verifications of GED degrees, please call (518) 474-5906   
or go to <http://www.emsc.nysed.gov/ged/contact.shtml>

For questions regarding professional licenses, professional license applications, or verifications of professional licenses,   
please call (518) 474-3817 or go to [http://www.op.nysed.gov](http://www.op.nysed.gov/)

For any questions regarding vocational rehabilitation, please call (518) 486-4031   
or go to [ http://www.vesid.nysed.gov/all/contact.htm](http://www.vesid.nysed.gov/all/contact.htm)
